Finding Aid for Program in American Culture (University of Michigan) records 1964-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Program in American Culture (University of Michigan) records 1964-1997, 1970-1992
University of Michigan. Program in American Culture.
5 linear feet
The Program in American Culture began in 1952 through the efforts of Professor Joe Lee Davis to study American life. The program achieved departmental status initially serving as a hub for interdisciplinary courses. In the 1970s the program and coursework expanded to include the study of women and minority groups with an emphasis on Latino Studies as well as art and media studies. Records include administrative files, directors correspondence, committee minutes, curriculum material, topical files, and material on faculty members and their activities.
0191 Bimu 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Program in American Culture in July 1999 (Donor no. 8858 ). Additional records transferred November 1999.
The Program in American Culture records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation and student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from the date of creation.
The University of Michigan Program in American Culture record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- removed to vault
The Program in American Culture at the University of Michigan began in 1952 through the efforts of English professor Joe Lee Davis and interested students. An early history of the program cites the reason for creation as the desire to provide students with the "opportunity to study American life from different points of view to get at the foundations of American culture." Before the existence of an actual American Culture program, graduate and undergraduate degrees in the American Culture area were administered through independent study. In 1952, the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies and the College of Literature, Science and the Arts decreed that the discipline should be recognized as a formal department. Following that recommendation, Professor Davis was appointed as its first director and an Executive Committee was created comprised of professors in other departments with American Culture interests. At this time, the department depended upon the willingness of other department faculty members to participate in offering American Culture courses. It is still the case that most American Culture professors are not solely appointed to the American Culture department, but also have joint appointments with other departments, such as English, History, or Women's Studies.
Since the birth of the department, the Program in American Culture philosophy has passed through several stages. In its early days the program revolved around the study of traditional American values and aspired to build bridges between the humanities and social sciences in order to gain a better understanding of these values. Since then however, the program has broadened its scope significantly and become a truly interdepartmental program. In the early 1970s, the program began to view itself as a facilitator for the study of all American cultures, not just the European-American culture. Taking into account America's ever-increasing diversity of national origins, races, religions, and social status, program coursework evolved to include in its curriculum the study of women, Asian American, African American, Hispanic American, Native American and other ethnic minority cultures.
The new study of other cultures in the 1970s helped to attract new faculty and further expand the program's scope. In 1984 for example, the program developed a curricular program in Latino/a Studies to address the growing societal and student interest in the history and study of Hispanic culture in America. Students from Latino/a Studies sought out other Latin American area classes and faculty in departments such as romance languages, history, sociology, and anthropology, adding new classes and bringing new faculty members to American Culture.
The original undergraduate curriculum consisted mainly of literature, history, and social studies courses, though students were permitted to select several courses from anthropology, economics, education, journalism, philosophy, political science, the fine arts, music, and speech. In 1970, the first core course, "American Values," was created in an effort to attract concentrators, bring a more unified approach to undergraduate concentration, and provide teaching opportunities for the program's graduate students. Curriculum changes persisted throughout the 1970s. Four different undergraduate tracks were created in English, history, the social sciences, and fine arts. A comparative culture component was added to allow students to study other cultures in addition to American culture. These tracks were later expanded, and as of 1994, consisted of seven tracks: Arts and Media, British and American Studies, Minority Studies, Intellectual History and Literature, Society and Politics, Latino/a Studies, and Self-Designed.
Masters and Ph.D. programs originally existed in the Program in American Culture. Journalists and teachers were frequent recipients of the American Culture masters degree. However, the masters program gradually declined until in 1974, it was only "reserved for unusual cases where it was inadvisable for students to continue into the Ph.D. program." The Ph.D. program, on the other hand, strengthened over time especially with the demise of the masters program. The papers illustrate the growth of the doctoral program to be increasingly sensitive to the diversity of American Culture.
Directors of the Program in American Culture
1952-1968 Joe Lee Davis
1969-1971 John Higham
1971-1978 Marvin Felheim
1978-1984 Robert Berkhofer
1984-1991 James McIntosh
1991-1994 June Howard
1994-1996 George Sánchez
1997- Richard Cándida-Smith
The Program in American Culture files are arranged in five series: Administrative Files, 1964-1997; Curriculum, 1969-1993; Latino/a Studies, 1984-1994; Relations, 1970-1997; and Faculty, 1970-1992. These series are not indicative of the original order of the files.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Program in American Culture.; National Characteristics, American.; Popular culture--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; Culture--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; Multiculturalism--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; United States--Intellectual life--20th century.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; United States--Social life and customs--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; United States--Civilization--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan.; Hispanic Americans--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Administrative Files 1964-1997
  Administrative Files, 1964-1997 contain the correspondence of five directors pertaining to Executive Committee matters. Also included in the series is a nearly complete set of Executive Committee minutes. The Evaluations subseries provides both an inside and an outside view of the program through documentation from 1) departmental reviews conducted by the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, and 2) an interesting critique of the program written by a former faculty member. Three folders of flyers from department-sponsored lectures and brown-bag talks illustrate the gradual change in program philosophy from the early 1970 emphasis on a single American experience to the later emphasis on the experiences of many different races, ethnicities, and socio-economic classes.
  - Director's Files
    - John Higham 1964-1971 (Box 1)
    - Marvin Felheim 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - Robert Berkhofer 1978-1984 (Box 1)
    - James McIntosh 1984-1990 (Box 1)
    - June Howard 1991 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee
    - Correspondence 1979-1992 (Box 1)
    - Elections 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes 1964-1992, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Evaluations
    - American Culture Critique 1985 (Box 1)
    - LS&A Review 1972-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Events/Awards
    - America as Text(s) Conference 1990 (Box 1)
    - Bicentennial Lecture 1975 (Box 1)
    - Brown Bag Presentations 1987-1993 (Box 1)
    - Conference on American Culture 1982 (Box 1)
    - Joe Lee Davis Memorial Fund 1975-1989 (Box 1)
    - Martin Luther King Symposium 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - Marvin Felheim Film Award 1980-1990 (Box 1)
    - Special Lectures Flyers 1970-1990, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Topical
    - Budget 1986-1992 (Box 2)
    - Graduate Candidacy Committee 1972-1976 (Box 2)
    - Grant Proposals 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Fundraising Committee 1974-1983 (Box 2)
    - Histories 1975-1993 (Box 2)
    - Newsletter 1970-1997, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Position Requests 1983-1992 (Box 2)
    - Program Policies 1973-1986 (Box 2)
- Curriculum 1969-1993
  Curriculum, 1969-1993 contains an expansive run of syllabi from undergraduate and graduate classes. Material contained in the topical subseries indicates the program's diverse interests in ethnic and minority cultures. Folders of material from Asian American, Native American, Latin American/Caribbean, and Puerto Rican studies are included in this subseries. The graduate subseries contains rich documentation regarding the continuing development of the doctoral program.
  Index to Syllabi, Course Names by Number
  (note: not all syllabi titles are included. Only those having distinct course titles are included.)
  101: Reading in America
  102: What is an American?
  201: American Values
  214: Introduction to Asian Studies
  260: Religion in America
  202: Community and Diversity in American Life, 1980-1985
  203: Varied titles about turn-of-the-century American Life
  205: American Cultures
  206: Topics in American Culture
  210: Topics in Ethnic Studies, 1985-1992
  211: Introduction to Latino Studies, 1990
  301: Topics in American Culture, 1987-1993
  304: American Immigration, 1989-1992
  310/311: Topics in Ethnic Studies, 1987-1989
  334: History and Philosophy of Dance in the Twentieth Century, 1972-1973
  340: History of Blacks in American Films, 1982
  350: Approaches to American Culture, 1976-1990
  372: American Technology and Society, 1981
  389: Reading Course in American Culture, 1976
  402: American Folklore, 1983
  403: American Philosophy, 1976
  404: Hispanic-Americans: Social Problems and Social Issues, 1988
  410: Topics in Chicano/Latino Studies, 1980-1987
  460: Algonquian Culture, 1980-1985
  490: American Film, 1973-1989
  498: Native American Literature, 1977-1987
  - Courses
    - 101, 102, 103, 214, 260 (Box 2)
    - 201 (Box 2)
    - 202 (Box 2)
    - 203 (Box 2)
    - 203 (undated) (Box 2)
    - 205,206 (Box 2)
    - 210 (Box 2)
    - 211 (Box 2)
    - 301 (Box 2)
    - 304 (Box 2)
    - 310, 311 (Box 2)
    - 334 (Box 2)
    - 340 (Box 2)
    - 350 (Box 2)
    - 372, 389, 398, 402, 403, 404, 460, 492, 498 (Box 2)
    - 410 (Box 2)
    - 490 (Box 2)
    - 496,499 (Box 2)
    - 500, 504, 530, 533, 596, 618, 621, 625 (Box 2)
    - 562 (Box 2)
    - 597, 598, 599 (Box 2)
    - 697, 699, 850 (Box 2)
  - Proposed Courses
    - Committee on Undergraduate Experiences (CUE) 1992 (Box 2)
    - Doctoral Program Majors 1969 (Box 2)
    - Midwestern Studies 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Project Community 1974-1978 (Box 2)
    - The Sixties 1991 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1976-1977, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Topical
    - American Culture Students Association 1969-1990 (Box 3)
    - Asian American Studies 1982-1992 (Box 3)
    - Beyond 1492, 1991-1993 (Box 3)
    - English Composition Board 1980-1992 (Box 3)
    - Ethnic Courses 1975-1985 (Box 3)
    - Exchange Programs 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Folklore 1975-1990 (Box 3)
    - Latin American/Caribbean Courses 1982-1991 (Box 3)
    - Mini Courses 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Native American Studies 1973-1992 (Box 3)
    - Puerto Rican Studies 1976-1985 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate
    - Career Guidance 1980-1987 (Box 3)
    - Concentration Planning 1963-1990 (Box 3)
    - Course Lists 1976-1989 (Box 3)
    - Curriculum Committee 1975-1992 (Box 3)
    - Experiential/Independent Study Courses 1975-1992 (Box 3)
  - Graduate
    - Admissions 1969-1991 (Box 3)
    - Cross-Cultural Project 1973-1991 (Box 3)
    - Curriculum Committee Proposals 1970-1989 (Box 3)
    - Doctoral Preliminary Examinations 1969-1991 (Box 3)
    - Doctoral Program Graduates 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - Language Requirement 1965-1994 (Box 3)
    - Masters Degree Screening Exam 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Minority Enrollment 1969-1988 (Box 3)
    - Program Descriptions 1964-1991 (Box 3)
    - Programs at Other Universities 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Student Statistics 1965-1986 (Box 3)
    - Task Force on Oppressed Minorities 1976-1980 (Box 3)
- Latino/a Studies 1984-1994
  The Latino/a Studies, 1984-1994 materials chronicle the program from its inception in 1984. This series contains material from faculty and director searches. Two files from the 1990-1992 director search containing applicant materials and search committee correspondence are restricted and have been physically removed from these records.
  - Advisory Committee Minutes and Correspondence 1984-1992 (Box 4)
  - Concentration Planning 1987-1990 (Box 4)
  - Courses 1987-1993 (Box 4)
  - History 1980-1986 (Box 4)
  - Program Review 1989 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Searches
    - Director 1990-1992
      - Applicants
        (RESTRICTED, removed to Vault Storage)
      - Search Committee Correspondence
    - Faculty Position Search
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - Visiting Assistant Hispanic-American Studies Professor 1984 (Box 4)
  - Special Lectures 1985-1992 (Box 4)
  - Teaching Assignments 1978-1992 (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate Initiatives Proposal 1987 (Box 4)
  - Visiting Professors 1991-1994 (Box 4)
- Relations 1970-1997
  Relations, 1970-1997 is a unique series that documents the large number of interdepartmental relations cultivated by the Program in American Culture. It includes correspondence between the program and the University of Michigan Institute for Gerontology, the Museum of Art, the Center for the Education of Women, and many others. Also included are three folders of correspondence between the program and American Culture departments at other universities.
  - University of Michigan Departments/Schools
    - Comparative Literature 1974-1981 (Box 4)
    - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching 1973-1977 (Box 4)
    - Communications 1971-1995 (Box 4)
    - Continuing Education for Women 1971-1994 (Box 4)
    - Education, School of 1973-1982 (Box 4)
    - English Language and Literature 1970-1992, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Film and Video Studies 1991-1997 (Box 4)
    - Flint Campus 1977 (Box 4)
    - Gerontology, Institute of 1979-1982 (Box 4)
    - History 1970-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - History of Art 1975-1992 (Box 4)
    - Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1973-1982 (Box 5)
    - Humanities Dept. in College of Engineering 1971-1988 (Box 5)
    - Information and Library Studies, School of 1971-1997 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Museum of Art 1971-1988 (Box 5)
    - Pilot Program 1972-1996 (Box 5)
    - Political Science 1980, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Program on Studies in Religion 1971-1994 (Box 5)
    - Sociology 1979 (Box 5)
    - Women's Studies 1972-1996, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Other Universities
    - 1970-1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976-1982 (Box 5)
    - 1983-1998 (Box 5)
- Faculty 1970-1992
  Faculty, 1970-1992 is a small series documenting the activity of American culture faculty members within and outside of their teaching and advising roles. Evidence of the involvement of American Culture faculty in the Michigan Society of Fellows, a university-wide faculty organization, as well as evidence of their involvement in the Faculty Associates, the small American Culture faculty reading group are provided. Two folders of faculty curriculum vitae, as well as a folder containing yearly lists of faculty members in other departments with interests in American Culture are included in this series. There is also substantial documentation regarding notable faculty member Marvin Felheim.
  - Appointment Correspondence 1970-1972 (Box 5)
  - American Area Faculty 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Curriculum Vitae 1991, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Faculty Seminar 1985-1992 (Box 5)
  - Faculty Service 1976-1984 (Box 5)
  - Individuals
    - Marvin Felheim
      - General 1973-1984 (Box 5)
      - Joe Lee Davis Professorship in American Culture 1979-1980 (Box 5)
      - Williams Award for Teaching in Humanities 1970 (Box 5)
    - Richard Rhodes 1980-1986 (Box 5)
  - Organizations
    - Cultural Studies Confederation 1990 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Associates 1987-1992 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Society of Fellows 1971-1992 (Box 5)